
Mizhodan (29 June 2017 [Beta])

   A basic two-dimensional Ordinary Kriging interpolator using an 
   exponential variogram model and all of the data. 

Usage: 
   Mizhodan <nugget> <sill> <range> <obs file> <targets file> <results file> 
   Mizhodan --help 
   Mizhodan --version 

Arguments: 
   <nugget>        The <nugget>, or 'nugget effect', is the discontinuity 
                   in the variogram at a lag of 0. The <nugget> quantifies 
                   the variance of the sampling and measurement errors and 
                   the hyper-local spatial variation. The units of the 
                   <nugget> are the units of the observed values squared. 
                   The <nugget> must be a strictly positive value. 

   <sill>          The <sill> is the value (height) at which variogram 
                   levels out. With the exponential model used in Mizhodan, 
                   the variogram approaches the <sill> asymptotically. 
                   In the common geostatistical framework (i.e. a second 
                   order stationary model), the sill equals the variance 
                   of the underlying population. The units of the <sill> 
                   are the units of the observed values squared. The <sill> 
                   must be a strictly positive value. 

   <range>         The <range> is the separation distance at which we 
                   model two observations as essentially uncorrelated. 
                   With the exponential model used in Mizhodan, this is 
                   the separation distance at which the variogram reaches 
                   95% of the <sill>. The units of the <range> are the 
                   units of the observations locations. The <range> must 
                   be a strictly positive value. 

   <obs file>      The <obs file> is the name of the file (including any 
                   necessary path information and the .csv file extension) 
                   containing the observation data. 

   <targets file>  The <target file> is the name of the file (including any 
                   necessary path information and the .csv file extension) 
                   containing the targets data. 

   <results file>  The <results filename> is the name of the file (including 
                   any necessary path information and the file extension) 
                   where Mizhodan will write all of the program results. 
                   If the specified <output file> already exists, it will 
                   be overwritten. 

Example: 
   Mizhodan 3 25 3500 obs.csv target.csv results.csv 

Observation File: 
   All of the observation head data are supplied by this .csv file. 

   The observation file contains no header line. The observation file may 
   include blank lines, which are ignored. The observation may include 
   comment lines, which are identified by an octothorpe (#) in the first 
   column of the line. 

   The observation file contains one line for each head observation. Each 
   line in the observation file has four fields. 

   <ID>            The observation identification string. The ID string can 
                   contain numbers, letters, underscores, and internal spaces. 
                   The ID may not contain commas. 

   <x>             The x-coordinate [L] of observation location. 

   <y>             The y-coordinate [L] of observation location. 

   <z>             The observation value. at location (x,y). 

   Each of the four fields must separated by a single comma. Spaces and tabs 
   at the start and end of fields are trimmed. 

Targets File: 
   All of the estimation targets are identified by this .csv file. 

   The target file contains no header line. The target file may include blank 
   lines, which are ignored. The observation may include comment lines, which 
   are identified by an octothorpe (#) in the first column of the line. 

   The targets file contains one line for each target location. Each 
   line in the target file has three fields. 

   <ID>            The target identification string. The ID string can 
                   contain numbers, letters, underscores, and internal spaces. 
                   The ID may not contain commas. 

   <x>             The x-coordinate [L] of target location. 

   <y>             The y-coordinate [L] of target location. 

   Each of the three fields must separated by a single comma. Spaces and tabs 
   at the start and end of fields are trimmed. 

Results File: 
   All of the program results are written to the results .csv file. 

   The results file contains one header line with five comma separated 
   text fields containing the field titles. 

   The rest of the output file comprises one line for each target. 
   Each line has five fields. 

   <ID>            The target identification string. 

   <x>             The x-coordinate for the location of the target. 

   <y>             The y-coordinate for the location of the target. 

   <Zhat>          The interpolated value at the target location. 

   <Kstd>          The 'standard error' of the interpolated value at the 
                   target location. The <Kstd> is the square root 
                   Ordinary Kriging variance. 

Notes: 
   o  An exponential variogram model is used. 
         gamma(h) = <nugget> + (<sill>-<nugget>)*(1 - exp(-3h/<range>)) 

   o  The project name 'Mizhodan' is the Ojibwe word for the inanimate 
      transitive verb 'hit it (in shooting)'. See [http://ojibwe.lib.umn.edu]. 

Authors: 
   Randal Barnes, University of Minnesota 
   William Olsen, Dakota County, Minnesota 

